{"text": "Action brought on 6 May 2020 – Rochem Group v EUIPO – Rochem Marine (ROCHEM)", "label": [[18, 28, "DATE"], [31, 43, "ORG"], [46, 51, "ORG"], [54, 67, "ORG"], [69, 75, "TITLE"]]}
{"text": "(Case T-261/20)", "label": []}
{"text": "Language of the case: English", "label": [[22, 29, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Parties", "label": []}
{"text": "Applicant: Rochem Group AG (Zug, Suisse) (represented by: P. Bogumil Franciszek, lawyer)", "label": [[11, 26, "ORG"], [28, 39, "LOC"], [58, 79, "PER"], [81, 87, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Trade mark at issue: International registration designating the European Union in respect of the figurative mark ROCHEM – International registration designating the European Union No 1 151 485", "label": [[60, 78, "LOC"], [113, 119, "TITLE"], [161, 179, "LOC"], [180, 192, "IDNUM"]]}
{"text": "Procedure before EUIPO: Cancellation proceedings", "label": [[17, 22, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "annul the contested decision;", "label": []}
{"text": "order EUIPO to render a new decision refusing the declaration of invalidity filed against the International trademark registration No 1 151 485, also for classes 11 and 40;", "label": [[6, 11, "ORG"], [131, 143, "IDNUM"]]}
{"text": "order EUIPO and the intervener, should the other party to the proceedings before the Board of Appeal appear before the Court, to pay its own costs and bear the fees and costs of the applicant.", "label": [[6, 11, "ORG"], [81, 100, "ORG"], [115, 124, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Infringement of Article 64(2) and (3) in connection with Article 198 of Regulation (EU) 2017/1001 of the European Parliament and of the Council.", "label": [[101, 124, "ORG"], [132, 143, "ORG"]]}
