{"text": "Action brought on 19 March 2021 – Union Syndicale Solidaires des SDIS de France et DOM/TOM v Commission", "label": [[18, 31, "DATE"], [34, 79, "ORG"], [83, 90, "ORG"], [93, 103, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(Case T-152/21)", "label": []}
{"text": "Language of the case: French", "label": [[22, 28, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Parties", "label": []}
{"text": "Applicant: Union Syndicale Solidaires des services départementaux d’incendie et de secours (SDIS) de France et DOM/TOM (Nîmes, France) (represented by: C. Johansson, lawyer)", "label": [[11, 107, "ORG"], [111, 118, "ORG"], [120, 133, "LOC"], [152, 164, "PER"], [166, 172, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Defendant: European Commission", "label": [[11, 30, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Form of order sought", "label": []}
{"text": "The applicant claims that the General Court should:", "label": [[26, 43, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "order the European Union (European Commission) to pay the applicant EUR 10 000 in compensation for the non-pecuniary harm which it suffered, with interest as set by the European Central Bank for capital refinancing operations, increased by three and a half percentage points;", "label": [[6, 24, "ORG"], [26, 45, "ORG"], [68, 71, "AMOUNT_UNIT"], [72, 78, "AMOUNT_VALUE"], [169, 190, "ORG"], [240, 256, "AMOUNT_VALUE"], [257, 274, "AMOUNT_UNIT"]]}
{"text": "hold the European Union (European Commission) liable for all the costs, in the amount of EUR 6 600.", "label": [[5, 23, "ORG"], [25, 44, "ORG"], [89, 92, "AMOUNT_UNIT"], [93, 98, "AMOUNT_VALUE"]]}
{"text": "Pleas in law and main arguments", "label": []}
{"text": "In support of its action for damages, the applicant criticises the Commission for not having responded for over a year and a half to the negligence complaint which it brought in respect of the French Republic. The applicant also complains that the Commission did not inform it promptly of the state of the assessment which it carried out and did not take a position on the complaint within a reasonable period of time. According to the applicant, the Commission therefore acted unlawfully, such as to give rise to non-contractual liability of the European Union.", "label": [[63, 77, "ORG"], [193, 208, "ORG"], [244, 258, "ORG"], [447, 461, "ORG"], [543, 561, "ORG"]]}
