{"text": "Action brought on 24 December 2021 – European Food v EUIPO – Société des produits Nestlé (FITNESS)", "label": [[18, 34, "DATE"], [37, 50, "ORG"], [53, 58, "ORG"], [61, 88, "ORG"], [90, 97, "TITLE"]]}
{"text": "(Case T-799/21)", "label": []}
{"text": "Language of the case: English", "label": [[22, 29, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Parties", "label": []}
{"text": "Applicant: European Food SA (Drăgăneşti, Romania) (represented by: K. Busch, lawyer)", "label": [[11, 27, "ORG"], [29, 48, "LOC"], [67, 75, "PER"], [77, 83, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Trade mark at issue: European Union word mark FITNESS – European Union trade mark No 2 470 326", "label": [[21, 35, "LOC"], [46, 53, "TITLE"], [56, 70, "LOC"], [82, 94, "IDNUM"]]}
{"text": "Procedure before EUIPO: Cancellation proceedings", "label": [[17, 22, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "annul the contested decision;", "label": []}
{"text": "as a secondary claim, alter the contested decision and grant the appeal filed against the decision rendered by the Cancellation Division in Cancellation Proceedings No 5 802 C;", "label": [[111, 136, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "order EUIPO to pay the costs.", "label": [[6, 11, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Infringement of Article 65(6) of Regulation (EC) 207/2009 of the Council;", "label": [[61, 72, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Infringement of Article 76 of Regulation (EC) 207/2009 of the Council, and of rules 37 and 50(1) of Commission Regulation (EC) No 2868/95;", "label": [[58, 69, "ORG"], [100, 110, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Infringement of Article 7(1)(b) in conjunction with Article 52(1)(a) of Regulation (EC) 207/2009 of the Council;", "label": [[100, 111, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Infringement of Article 7(1)(c) in conjunction with Article 52(1)(2) of Regulation (EC) 207/2009 of the Council.", "label": [[100, 111, "ORG"]]}
