{"text": "Order of the Court (Ninth Chamber) of 6 May 2020 — Kersting Horváth v European Parliament", "label": [[9, 34, "ORG"], [38, 48, "DATE"], [51, 67, "PER"], [70, 89, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(Case C-628/19 P)", "label": []}
{"text": "(Appeal — European Parliament — Rules governing the payment of expenses and allowances to Members of the European Parliament — Parliamentary assistance allowance — Recovery of sums unduly paid)", "label": [[10, 29, "ORG"], [101, 124, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Language of the case: Hungarian", "label": [[22, 31, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Parties", "label": []}
{"text": "Appellant: Kersting Horváth (represented by: Y. Kuzmenko, ügyvéd)", "label": [[11, 27, "PER"], [45, 56, "PER"], [58, 64, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Other party to the proceedings: European Parliament (represented by: H. Gerasimov and L. Torres, acting as Agents)", "label": [[32, 51, "ORG"], [69, 81, "PER"], [86, 95, "PER"], [107, 113, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Operative part of the order", "label": []}
{"text": "The appeal is dismissed as manifestly unfounded.", "label": []}
{"text": "Mr Kersting Horváth is ordered to pay the costs.", "label": [[0, 19, "PER"]]}
{"text": "OJ C 372, 4.11.2019.", "label": [[10, 19, "DATE"]]}
