{"text": "Order of the President of the General Court of 4 May 2020 – Morozov and Others v Commission", "label": [[13, 22, "PROFESSION"], [26, 43, "ORG"], [47, 57, "DATE"], [60, 67, "PER"], [81, 91, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(Case T‑146/20 R)", "label": []}
{"text": "(Application for interim measures – Civil service – Elections for the Luxembourg local section of the Commission’s Staff Committee – Regularity – Supervisory obligation of the institution – Application for interim measures – No prima facie case)", "label": [[70, 80, "LOC"], [102, 130, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "1. Application for interim relief – Suspension of operation of a measure – Interim measures – Conditions for granting – Prima facie case – Urgency – Serious and irreparable damage – Cumulative nature – Order of examination and method of verification – Discretion of the court hearing the application for interim relief – Balancing of all the interests involved", "label": []}
{"text": "(Arts 256(1), 278 and 279 TFEU; Rules of Procedure of the General Court, Art. 156(3))", "label": [[54, 71, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(see paras 17-20, 26)", "label": []}
{"text": "2. Officials – Representation – Staff Committee – Elections – Regularity – Obligation of the institutions to ensure the regularity of electoral operations – Scope", "label": [[32, 47, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(Staff Regulations of Officials, Arts 9(2), 90 and 91)", "label": []}
{"text": "(see paras 24, 25)", "label": []}
{"text": "3. Officials – Representation – Staff Committee – Elections – Scheme applicable to the Central Committee and the local sections of the Commission’s Staff Committee – Information to be brought to the attention of voters – Affiliation or support of a candidate by a trade union or professional organisation – Optional and secondary element", "label": [[32, 47, "ORG"], [87, 104, "ORG"], [131, 163, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(Staff Regulations of Officials, Art. 9(2))", "label": []}
{"text": "(see paras 36-38)", "label": []}
{"text": "Re:", "label": []}
{"text": "Application based on Article 270 TFEU and Article 91(4) of the Staff Regulations of Officials of the European Union seeking, principally, in the first place, suspension of the operation of (i) the memo of 26 November 2019 from the polling office declaring the results of the elections for the Luxembourg local section of the Commission’s Staff Committee, (ii) the Commission’s decision of 28 November 2019 concerning the calculation of the representativeness of representative trade unions and staff associations in the institution, (iii) the mandate of the Luxembourg local section of the Commission’s Staff Committee resulting from the elections of November 2019, (iv) the appointment by the Luxembourg local section of the Commission’s Staff Committee of its delegates to the Commission’s Central Staff Committee, and (v) any other decision concerning the allocation of additional resources to the Commission’s staff representatives, and, in the second place, an order requiring the Commission to retain the outgoing Staff Committee until the judgment is handed down in the main proceedings, while limiting its mandate to current business, and, in the alternative, an order requiring the Commission, first, to limit to current business the mandate of the Luxembourg local section of the Commission’s Staff Committee resulting from the elections of November 2019 and, second, an order requiring that local section to appoint to the Commission’s Central Staff Committee the representatives proposed by Union Syndicale Luxembourg.", "label": [[97, 115, "LOC"], [205, 221, "DATE"], [293, 303, "LOC"], [321, 353, "ORG"], [360, 376, "ORG"], [389, 405, "DATE"], [558, 568, "LOC"], [586, 618, "ORG"], [651, 664, "DATE"], [694, 704, "LOC"], [722, 754, "ORG"], [762, 771, "PROFESSION"], [779, 815, "ORG"], [897, 913, "ORG"], [920, 935, "PROFESSION"], [982, 996, "ORG"], [1020, 1035, "ORG"], [1187, 1201, "ORG"], [1258, 1268, "LOC"], [1286, 1318, "ORG"], [1351, 1364, "DATE"], [1430, 1470, "ORG"], [1475, 1490, "PROFESSION"], [1503, 1529, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Operative part", "label": []}
{"text": "1. The application for interim measures is dismissed.", "label": []}
{"text": "2. The costs are reserved.", "label": []}
