{"text": "Action brought on 31 July 2020 – Tecnica Group v EUIPO – Zeitneu (Shape of a boot)", "label": [[18, 30, "DATE"], [33, 46, "ORG"], [49, 54, "ORG"], [57, 64, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(Case T-483/20)", "label": []}
{"text": "Language of the case: English", "label": [[22, 29, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Parties", "label": []}
{"text": "Applicant: Tecnica Group SpA (Giavera del Montello, Italy) (represented by: L. Danilova, lawyer)", "label": [[11, 28, "ORG"], [30, 57, "LOC"], [76, 87, "PER"], [89, 95, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Trade mark at issue: European Union tridimensional mark (Shape of a boot) – European Union trade mark No 10 168 441", "label": [[21, 35, "LOC"], [76, 90, "LOC"], [102, 115, "IDNUM"]]}
{"text": "Procedure before EUIPO: Cancellation proceedings", "label": [[17, 22, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "annul the contested decision;", "label": []}
{"text": "order EUIPO and the intervener to pay the costs.", "label": [[6, 11, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Pleas in law", "label": []}
{"text": "Infringement of the principles of legality, equal treatment and sound administration under Articles 123 and 124 of Regulation (EU) 2017/1001 of the European Parliament and of the Council;", "label": [[144, 167, "ORG"], [175, 186, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Infringement of the principle of protection of legitimate expectations under Articles 123 and 124 of Regulation (EU) 2017/1001 of the European Parliament and of the Council;", "label": [[130, 153, "ORG"], [161, 172, "ORG"]]}
