{"text": "Request for a preliminary ruling from the Consiglio di Stato (Italy) lodged on 28 September 2020 – Sisal Entertainment SpA v Agenzia delle Dogane e dei Monopoli", "label": [[42, 60, "ORG"], [62, 67, "LOC"], [79, 96, "DATE"], [99, 122, "ORG"], [125, 160, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(Case C-480/20)", "label": []}
{"text": "Language of the case: Italian", "label": [[22, 29, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Referring court", "label": []}
{"text": "Consiglio di Stato", "label": [[0, 18, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Parties to the main proceedings", "label": []}
{"text": "Appellant: Sisal Entertainment SpA", "label": [[11, 34, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Respondent: Agenzia delle Dogane e dei Monopoli", "label": [[12, 47, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Questions referred", "label": []}
{"text": "Is the introduction of a provision, such as that contained in Article 1(649) of Law 190/14, which reduces commission and fees only in respect of a specific and limited category of operator, namely operators of games played on gaming machines, and not all operators in the gaming sector, compatible with the exercise of the freedom of establishment guaranteed by Article 49 TFEU and with the exercise of the freedom to provide services guaranteed by Article 56 TFEU?", "label": []}
{"text": "Is the introduction of the abovementioned provision contained in Article 1(649) of Law 190/14, which for economic reasons alone reduced the fees agreed to in a concession agreement concluded between a company and an Italian State authority during the term of that agreement, compatible with the EU-law principle of the protection of legitimate expectations?", "label": [[216, 239, "ORG"], [295, 297, "LOC"]]}
