{"text": "Action brought on 18 November 2020 – Canisius v EUIPO – Beiersdorf (CCLABELLE VIENNA)", "label": [[18, 34, "DATE"], [37, 45, "ORG"], [48, 53, "ORG"], [56, 66, "ORG"], [68, 84, "TITLE"]]}
{"text": "(Case T-694/20)", "label": []}
{"text": "Language of the case: English", "label": [[22, 29, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Parties", "label": []}
{"text": "Applicant: Zaharia Klara Omelius (Vienna, Austria) (represented by: B. Ponomarenko, lawyer)", "label": [[11, 32, "PER"], [34, 49, "LOC"], [68, 82, "PER"], [84, 90, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Contested decision: Decision of the Fourth Board of Appeal of EUIPO of 16 September 2020 in Case R 2233/2019-4", "label": [[32, 67, "ORG"], [71, 88, "DATE"]]}
{"text": "partially annul the contested decision insofar as the opposition was upheld in respect of the goods in Classes 3 and 16;", "label": []}
{"text": "order the defendant and Beiersdorf, should Beiersdorf join this proceeding, to pay its own costs and to bear all the fees and costs of the applicant;", "label": [[24, 34, "ORG"], [43, 53, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "dismiss the opposition brought by Beiersdorf against the registration of application No 17 592 461 and order EUIPO to allow the (contested) application No 17 592 461 to proceed to the registration in relation to all goods and services applied for in Classes 3, 16, and 25 as well as order Beiersdorf to bear its own costs and pay all the fees and costs incurred by the applicant due to the opposition proceedings.", "label": [[34, 44, "ORG"], [85, 98, "IDNUM"], [109, 114, "ORG"], [152, 165, "IDNUM"], [289, 299, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Pleas in law", "label": []}
