{"text": "Judgment of the Court (First Chamber) of 25 February 2021 – Peter Portelli v European Commission", "label": [[12, 37, "ORG"], [41, 57, "DATE"], [60, 74, "PER"], [77, 96, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(Case C-615/19 P)", "label": []}
{"text": "(Appeal – Action for damages – Non-contractual liability of the European Union – Allegedly illegal conduct of the European Commission and the European Anti-Fraud Office (OLAF) – Termination of office of a Member of the Commission – Procedural rules governing the OLAF investigation – Opening of an investigation – Right to be heard – OLAF Supervisory Committee – Presumption of innocence – Assessment of the alleged damage)", "label": [[60, 78, "LOC"], [110, 133, "ORG"], [142, 175, "ORG"], [215, 229, "ORG"], [263, 267, "ORG"], [334, 360, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Language of the case: English", "label": [[22, 29, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Parties", "label": []}
{"text": "Appellant: Peter Portelli (represented by: G. Allen and E. Robertson, avocats)", "label": [[11, 25, "PER"], [43, 51, "PER"], [56, 68, "PER"], [70, 77, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Other party to the proceedings: European Commission (represented by: I. Z. Etienne and B. Ampuero Silva, acting as Agents)", "label": [[32, 51, "ORG"], [69, 82, "PER"], [87, 103, "PER"], [115, 121, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Operative part of the judgment", "label": []}
{"text": "The Court:", "label": [[0, 9, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Dismisses the appeal;", "label": []}
{"text": "Orders Mr Peter Portelli to bear his own costs and to pay those incurred by the European Commission.", "label": [[7, 24, "PER"], [76, 99, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "____________", "label": []}
{"text": "OJ C 328, 30.9.2019.", "label": [[10, 19, "DATE"]]}
