{"text": "Judgment of the General Court of 24 February 2021 – Universität Koblenz-Landau v EACEA", "label": [[12, 29, "ORG"], [33, 49, "DATE"], [52, 78, "ORG"], [81, 86, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(Case T-606/18)", "label": []}
{"text": "(Arbitration clause – Tempus Programmes – Grant agreement – Eligible costs – Suspension of payments – Repayment of amounts paid – Obligation to state reasons)", "label": []}
{"text": "Language of the case: German", "label": [[22, 28, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Parties", "label": []}
{"text": "Applicant: Universität Koblenz-Landau (Mainz, Germany) (represented by: A. von der Groeben and G. Kaufmann, lawyers)", "label": [[11, 37, "ORG"], [39, 53, "LOC"], [72, 90, "PER"], [95, 106, "PER"], [108, 115, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Defendant: Education, Audiovisual and Culture Executive Agency (represented by: B. Thomson, acting as Agent, and L. van der Berg and N. Dixon, lawyers)", "label": [[11, 62, "ORG"], [80, 90, "PER"], [102, 107, "PROFESSION"], [113, 128, "PER"], [133, 141, "PER"], [143, 150, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Re:", "label": []}
{"text": "Application under Article 272 TFEU asking the General Court, first, to declare that the EACEA is not owed a debt of EUR 22 452.22, to which the latter claims to be entitled in respect of the performance of Grant Agreement No. 2012-3075 concerning the implementation of the project ‘Qualification Frameworks in Central Asia: Bologna-Based Principles and Regional Coordination’, and, secondly, to order EACEA to pay the applicant a sum of EUR 41 408.15 under that agreement, together with default interest.", "label": [[42, 59, "ORG"], [88, 93, "ORG"], [116, 119, "AMOUNT_UNIT"], [120, 129, "AMOUNT_VALUE"], [310, 322, "LOC"], [324, 331, "LOC"], [401, 406, "ORG"], [437, 440, "AMOUNT_UNIT"], [441, 450, "AMOUNT_VALUE"]]}
{"text": "Operative part of the judgment", "label": []}
{"text": "The Court:", "label": [[0, 9, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Dismisses the action;", "label": []}
{"text": "Orders Universität Koblenz-Landau to pay the costs.", "label": [[7, 33, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "____________", "label": []}
{"text": "OJ C 427, 26.11.2018.", "label": [[10, 20, "DATE"]]}
