{"text": "Appeal brought on 1 February 2021 by Embutidos Monells, SA against the judgment of the General Court (Fifth Chamber) delivered on 2 December 2020 in Case T-639/19, Salazar Meringo Canales v EUIPO – Embutidos Monells (5MS MMMMM)", "label": [[18, 33, "DATE"], [37, 58, "ORG"], [83, 116, "ORG"], [130, 145, "DATE"], [164, 187, "PER"], [190, 195, "ORG"], [198, 215, "ORG"], [217, 226, "TITLE"]]}
{"text": "(Case C-59/21 P)", "label": []}
{"text": "Language of the case: Spanish", "label": [[22, 29, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Parties", "label": []}
{"text": "Appellant: Embutidos Monells, SA (represented by: C. Albanez Acosta and U. Ceruti Cortés, abogados)", "label": [[11, 32, "ORG"], [50, 67, "PER"], [72, 88, "PER"], [90, 98, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Other parties to the proceedings: Salazar Meringo Canales, S. A. U., European Union Intellectual Property Office", "label": [[34, 57, "PER"], [59, 67, "ORG"], [69, 112, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "By order of 18 May 2021, the Court of Justice (Chamber determining whether appeals may proceed) ruled that the appeal should not be allowed to proceed and ordered Embutidos Monells, SA to bear its own costs.", "label": [[12, 23, "DATE"], [25, 95, "ORG"], [163, 184, "ORG"]]}
