{"text": "Judgment of the General Court (Second Chamber) of 21 December 2021 – EFFAS v EUIPO – CFA Institute (CEFA Certified European Financial Analyst)", "label": [[12, 46, "ORG"], [50, 66, "DATE"], [69, 74, "ORG"], [77, 82, "ORG"], [85, 98, "ORG"], [100, 141, "TITLE"]]}
{"text": "(Case T‑369/20)", "label": []}
{"text": "(EU trade mark – Opposition proceedings – Application for the EU word mark CEFA Certified European Financial Analyst – Earlier EU word mark CFA – Relative ground for refusal – Article 8(1)(b) of Regulation (EC) No 207/2009 (now Article 8(1)(b) of Regulation (EU) 2017/1001))", "label": [[1, 3, "LOC"], [62, 64, "LOC"], [75, 116, "TITLE"], [127, 129, "LOC"], [140, 143, "TITLE"]]}
{"text": "1. EU trade mark – Definition and acquisition of the EU trade mark – Relative grounds for refusal – Opposition by the proprietor of an earlier identical or similar mark registered for identical or similar goods or services – Likelihood of confusion with the earlier mark – Criteria for assessment", "label": [[3, 5, "LOC"], [53, 55, "LOC"]]}
{"text": "(Council Regulation No 207/2009, Art. 8(1)(b))", "label": [[1, 8, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(see paras 19-21)", "label": []}
{"text": "2. EU trade mark – Definition and acquisition of the EU trade mark – Relative grounds for refusal – Opposition by the proprietor of an earlier identical or similar mark registered for identical or similar goods or services – Likelihood of confusion with the earlier mark – Assessment of the likelihood of confusion – Determination of the relevant public – Attention level of the public – Education and training services", "label": [[3, 5, "LOC"], [53, 55, "LOC"]]}
{"text": "(Council Regulation No 207/2009, Art. 8(1)(b))", "label": [[1, 8, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(see paras 28, 29, 31)", "label": []}
{"text": "3. EU trade mark – Definition and acquisition of the EU trade mark – Relative grounds for refusal – Opposition by the proprietor of an earlier identical or similar mark registered for identical or similar goods or services – Likelihood of confusion with the earlier mark – Word marks CEFA Certified European Financial Analyst and CFA", "label": [[3, 5, "LOC"], [53, 55, "LOC"], [284, 325, "TITLE"], [330, 333, "TITLE"]]}
{"text": "(Council Regulation No 207/2009, Art. 8(1)(b))", "label": [[1, 8, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(see paras 32, 34, 35, 47-49)", "label": []}
{"text": "4. EU trade mark – Definition and acquisition of the EU trade mark – Relative grounds for refusal – Opposition by the proprietor of an earlier identical or similar mark registered for identical or similar goods or services – Likelihood of confusion with the earlier mark – Likelihood of association – Earlier marks exhibiting characteristics enabling them to be regarded as forming part of the same series or family – Conditions", "label": [[3, 5, "LOC"], [53, 55, "LOC"]]}
{"text": "(Council Regulation No 207/2009, Art. 8(1)(b))", "label": [[1, 8, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(see para. 45)", "label": []}
{"text": "Re:", "label": []}
{"text": "Action brought against the decision of the Fifth Board of Appeal of EUIPO of 31 March 2020 (Case R 1082/2019-5), relating to opposition proceedings between CFA Institute and EFFAS.", "label": [[39, 73, "ORG"], [77, 90, "DATE"], [156, 169, "ORG"], [174, 179, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Operative part", "label": []}
{"text": "The Court:", "label": [[0, 9, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "1.", "label": []}
{"text": "Annuls the decision of the Fifth Board of Appeal of the European Union Intellectual Property Office (EUIPO) of 31 March 2020 (R 1082/2019-5);", "label": [[23, 107, "ORG"], [111, 124, "DATE"]]}
{"text": "2.", "label": []}
{"text": "Orders EUIPO to bear its own costs and to pay those incurred by European Federation of Financial Analysts’ Societies (EFFAS);", "label": [[7, 12, "ORG"], [64, 124, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "3.", "label": []}
{"text": "Orders CFA Institute to bear its own costs.", "label": [[7, 20, "ORG"]]}
