{"text": "Action brought on 4 April 2022 – Luis and Others v Commission", "label": [[18, 30, "DATE"], [33, 37, "PER"], [51, 61, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "(Case T-177/22)", "label": []}
{"text": "Language of the case: French", "label": [[22, 28, "NATIONALITY"]]}
{"text": "Parties", "label": []}
{"text": "Applicants: A. Luis (Barcelona, Spain) and nine other applicants (represented by: W. de Santis, lawyer)", "label": [[12, 19, "PER"], [21, 37, "LOC"], [82, 94, "PER"], [96, 102, "PROFESSION"]]}
{"text": "Defendant: European Commission", "label": [[11, 30, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "Form of order sought", "label": []}
{"text": "The applicants claim that the Court should:", "label": [[26, 35, "ORG"]]}
{"text": "annul the applicants’ payslips for June 2021 in so far as they are indicative of a decision to withdraw the flat-rate allowance owed by way of reimbursement of the costs of travelling from the place of employment to the place of origin;", "label": [[35, 44, "DATE"]]}
{"text": "annul, in so far as it supplements the statement of reasons for the contested decision, the decision of 22 December 2021 rejecting the complaint of 30 August 2021;", "label": [[104, 120, "DATE"], [148, 162, "DATE"]]}
{"text": "order the defendant to pay the costs.", "label": []}
{"text": "Pleas in law and main arguments", "label": []}
{"text": "In support of the action, the applicants rely on three pleas in law, which are, in essence, identical or similar to those relied on in Case T-177/22, Arslan v Commission.", "label": [[150, 156, "PER"], [159, 169, "ORG"]]}
